Mona Bartling

Department of Geoinformatics – Z_GIS
University of Salzburg
Schillerstraße 30
5020 Salzburg
mona.bartling@sbg.ac.at | +43 (0) 662 8044 7553
<u>University of Salzburg | Google Scholar</u>

ORCID: 0000-0001-8362-7543

I am a doctoral student and researcher in geoinformatics with a strong focus on map design usability, map use context, and map design adaptations. I have 5+ years work experiences in the sector of digital agriculture with work appointments in various international research institutes. I have a passion for cartographic design, and I am aiming to look at the margins of map design solutions.

EDUCATION

Since 2017 Doctoral program in Applied Geoinformatics
Associated (since 2017) and FWF-funded (since 2020) student at the Doctoral
College GIScience
Department of Geoinformatics – Z_GIS, University of Salzburg, Austria
Thesis: The impact of user context on map design usability
Advisor: Prof. Thomas Blaschke

2015 M.Sc. Applied Geoinformatics (graduated with 1.1)

University of Salzburg, Austria

Offiversity of Salzburg, Austria

B.A. Educational Science (focus Geography; graduated with 1.7)

University of Bremen, Germany

RESEARCH POSITIONS

Since 2020 Researcher at the Doctoral College GIScience, Department of Geoinformatics – Z_GIS, University of Salzburg, Austria
Research focus on analyzing user-centered design approaches for context-based map design usability.

2017-2019 Researcher at the Department of Geoinformatics – Z_GIS, University of Salzburg, Austria – BMZ funded project "Climate smart coffee and cocoa: from theory to practice (CSCC)" with research appointments at the International Center for

Austria – BMZ funded project "Climate smart coffee and cocoa: from theory to practice (CSCC)" with research appointments at the International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT), Cali, Colombia and the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA), Kampala, Uganda

Research focus on designing mapping tools for citizen participation and farmer collaboration.

2015-2017 Visiting researcher at the International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT),

Cali, Colombia

Research focus on the design of offline maps and the usability of collaborative mobile map applications for smallholder farmers.

2014-2015 Research assistant at RSA, Studio iSPACE, Salzburg, Austria

Research focus on the evaluation of a demand potential for the public transportation system of Salzburg.

2013 Research assistant at the Centre for Demographic and Health Research (CIDS),
UNAN-León, Nicaragua
Research focus on geoprocessing and spatial analysis of demographic data.

2011 Research assistant at the Department of Geography, University of Bremen,
Germany

Research focus on spatial analyses for the development of a Business

Improvement District in Bremen.

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AFFILIATIONS

Since 2020	NACIS membership
Since 2017	Associate student at the Doctoral College GIScience, Department of
	Geoinformatics – Z_GIS, University of Salzburg, Austria
2015-2020	Thesis coordinator of the academic committee at UNIGIS, Latin America
2013-2014	DAAD scholarship (German Academic Exchange Service) for a 12-months study
	appointment at UNAN-León, Nicaragua
2013	Associate of the Salzburg-León city cooperation
2011-2012	Erasmus scholarship for a 6-months study appointment at the University of
	Gothenburg, Sweden

RESEARCH

PUBLISHED ARTICLES

Bartling, M., Robinson, A. C., Resch, B., Eitzinger, A., & Atzmanstorfer, K. (2021). The Role of User Context in the Design of Mobile Map Applications. Cartography and Geographic Information Science. https://doi.org/10.1080/15230406.2021.1933595

Bartling, M., Resch, B., Trösterer, S., & Eitzinger, A. (2021). Evaluating PPGIS Usability in a Multi-National Field Study Combining Qualitative Surveys and Eye-Tracking. The Cartographic Journal. https://doi.org/10.1080/00087041.2020.1842143

Eitzinger, A., Bartling, M., Feil, C., Bonilla-Findji, O., Andrieu, N., & Jarvis, A. (2020). GeoFarmer App: A tool to complement extension services and foster active farmers participation and knowledge exchange. Report available: https://cgspace.cgiar.org/handle/10568/107365

Eitzinger, A., Cock, J., Atzmanstorfer, K., Binder, C. R., Läderach, P., Bonilla-Findji, O., Bartling, M., ... & Jarvis, A. (2019). GeoFarmer: A monitoring and feedback system for agricultural development projects. *Computers and electronics in agriculture*, *158*, 109-121. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compag.2019.01.049

Bartling, M., Resch, B., Eitzinger, A., & Zurita-Arthos, L. (2019). A multi-national human-computer interaction evaluation of the public participatory GIS GeoCitizen. *GI_Forum 2019*,, 7, 19-39. DOI: 10.1553/giscience2019_01_s18

Bartling, M., Sotelo, S., Eitzinger, A., & Atzmanstorfer, K. (2016). Press the Button: Online/Offline Mobile Applications in an Agricultural Context. *GI_Forum 2016*,, *4*, 106-116. DOI: 10.1553/giscience2016_01_s106

Sudmanns, M., Cadus, S., & Bartling, M. (2015). Geodata-based Alerting Service (GAS): A Conceptual Framework to Create Notifications Based on Spatial and Temporal Data. *GI_Forum*, 2015, 6-15. DOI:10.1553/giscience2015s6

SELECTED CONFERENCE, WEBINAR, AND WORKSHOP PRESENTATIONS

- "When things go wrong –conducting research during a pandemic" ICA workshop on Adaptable Research Methods For Empirical Research with Map Users (cogvis.icaci.org/21_adaptable.html)
- "Digital tools for farmers advisory and climate action" online webinar series of the CGIAR Platform for Big Data in Agriculture (bigdata.cgiar.org/blog-post/webinar-digital-tools-for-farmers-advisory-and-climate-action)
- 2019 "A multi-national human–computer interaction evaluation of the public participatory GIS GeoCitizen" GI_Forum conference presentation, Salzburg, Austria
- 2018 "Smart monitoring of farm labor productivity" pitch invitation as one of the inspire challenge finalists at the Big Data in Agriculture Convention 2018, Nairobi, Kenya
- 2017 "'Flat' Learning Alliance for Extension" pitch invitation as one of the inspire challenge finalists at the Big Data in Agriculture Convention 2017, Cali, Colombia